[Music]
you can do all kinds of fancy stuff with
reinforcement learning right so the Crux
in reinforcement learning is that uh the
agent is going to that is this learning
agent right it's going to learn in close
interaction with an environment right so
the environment could be the hel opter
it could be the cycle right and uh or it
could be your back gam and board and
your opponent all of this could
constitute the environment a variety of
different choices so you sense the state
in which the environment is
in right you sense the state of the
environment okay and figure out what is
the action that you should take in
response to the state right so you apply
the action back to the environment this
causes a change in the state right so
now comes at to keeper right so you
should not just choose actions that are
beneficial in the current state but you
should choose actions in such a way that
they'll put you in a
state which is beneficial for you in the
future right just just capturing the
queen of of your opponent is not enough
on the chest that might give you a high
reward but it might put you in a really
bad position so you don't want that
right you really want to be uh looking
at the entire sequence of decisions that
you're going to have to make and then
try to behave optimally with respect to
that right so what what do we mean by
behave optimally in this case right
we're going to assume that the
environment right is giving you some
kind of an evaluation like falling down
HTS right or capturing a piece maybe
gives you a a small plus. five or
winning the game gives you like 100
right so every time you win every time
you make a move or every time you
execute an action you did not get a
reward or you did not get an evaluation
from the environment right so it could
be just zero it could be could be
nothing right so I should point out that
this whole idea of having an evaluation
come from the environment is is just a
mathematical convenience that we have
here uh but in reality if you think
about biological systems that are
learning using reinforcement learning
right all they are getting is their
usual sensory
inputs right so there is some fraction
in the brain okay that sits there and
interprets some of those sensory input
as Rewards or
punishments right so you fall down you
get hurt I mean that's still a sensory
input that is coming from your skin
right or somebody Pats you on a back
that's still a sensory input that comes
from the skin right it's just another
kind of an input right so you could
choose to interpret this as a reward
right or this as a collision with an
obstacle if something is brushing
against my shoulder let me move away
right or you can just take it as
somebody's patting my back so I did
something good right so it's a matter of
interpretation so this is uh this whole
thing about having a state signal and
having a separate evaluation coming from
the environment is a fiction right that
is created to have a clear cleaner
mathematical model but in reality things
are a lot Messier you know you don't you
don't have such a clean separation right
and like I said uh so you have a
stochastic environment you have uh
delayed evaluation noisy so the new term
that we have added here
is
huh noisy
scalar the new term we have had today is
scalar so that is one of the things with
uh the classical reinforcement learning
approaches he said I'm going to assume
that my reward is a scalar signal right
so we talked about getting hurt and
having food and so on so forth what all
of this will happen mathematically is
I'll convert that into some kind of a
number on a scale right so getting hurt
might be minus
100 right getting food might be plus 5
winning the game might be+ 20 right
capturing a piece might be
plus5 or something like that so I'm
going to convert them to a scale right
and the goal is now now that I have a
single number that represents the
evaluation the goal is now to get as
much as possible of that quantity over
the long
run okay make
sense right so if you have questions
doubts stop me and ask so mathematically
a scalar is easier to optimize
uh not necessarily right I'm just
talking about so it's it's like a cost
function if you want to think about it
in in terms of in terms of control
systems right so this is like a cost and
I'm trying to optimize the cost right
and uh so if the cost is going to be
Vector valued then I have to start
trading off one One Direction of the
vector against the other so which
component of the vector is more
important so then it get into all kinds
of uh so par optimality kind of
questions and so it's not really clear
uh what exactly is optimal in such cases
right so in fact later on I we have
homework exercise for you to argue for
and against scalar rewards so you can
put down your thoughts then right uh so
here again let me emphasize it's not
supervised learning right in supervised
learning this is essentially what you're
going to see there will be an input and
there will be an output that you
producing and somebody will be giving
you a Target output okay so this is what
you're supposed to produce and
essentially you come compare the output
you are producing to the Target output
right and you can form some error signal
right and you can use that error in
order to train your agent right you can
try to minimize the error you can do
gradient descent on the error or you can
do variety of things and you can try to
train the agent so here I don't have a
Target I do have to learn mapping from
the input to the output but I don't have
a Target and hence I can't form an error
right and therefore my trial and error
becomes very
essential so if I have errors right I
can form gradients of errors and they
can go in the opposite direction of the
gradient of the error right and then
that gives me some uh direction in which
to change my parameters right that
constitute the agent right agent is
going to be described in some way right
the error gives me a direction right but
now since I I don't know a direction
right so I just I do something I get one
evaluation so I don't know whether the
evaluation is good or bad right so think
of writing an exam right I don't tell
you the right answer I just tell you
three right and so what do you do now do
are you happy with the answer should you
change
it should you change it in One Direction
or should you change it in the other
direction see what makes it even more
tricky is I don't you don't even know
how much the exam is out
of so when I say three it could be three
out of
three it could be three out of
100 right and or it could be like three
out of
18 which was what a class average in ml
in the first
place uh right uh so it could be any of
these things right so you don't even
know whether three is a good number or a
bad number so you have to explore to
figure out a if I can get higher than
three right or three is the best the
second thing is okay if I can get higher
than three how should I change my
parameters to get to become higher than
three right so I have to change my
parameters a little bit that way
okay I have to change the parameters a
little bit this way right so if I'm
cycling right I have to push down a
little harder on the pedal okay or I
have to push down a little softer on the
pedal to figure out whether I'm staying
balanced for a longer period of time or
not right so I don't know that otherwise
unless I try these things I wouldn't
know this is why the trial and error
part so if I push down a little harder
and I stay balanced maybe I should try
pushing down even more harder next time
right so maybe that'll make it better
right and then there might be some point
where I tip over so I need to come back
so this is some things which you have to
try unless you try that you don't even
know which direction you have to move in
right so this is much more than just the
psychological aspects of traal and error
there's also a mathematical reason if
you want to adapt my parameters right I
need to know the gradient so that you
need to do this yeah reward come in the
previous
picture uh the reward is the one that
uh I know that gives you the evaluation
for the
output right so here uh in the
supervised case the error is the
evaluation for the output if the error
is zero then your output is perfect
right but then you have a way of gauging
what the error is because you have a
Target to which you can compare right
and from there you get the error so in
the reinforcement learning case the
evaluation is directly given to you as
the uh the evaluation of the output
right it's not necessarily comparing
against Target value or anything you
don't know how the evaluation was
generated right you just get an
evaluation directly so you you just get
some number corresponding to the output
right so maybe I should have done put an
arrow from the top saying evaluation
comes in from there but uh but that's
exactly where it's coming it's a
substitute for the error signal but just
that you don't know what the evaluation
is of course the way it differs from the
error is the minor difference is you
typically tend to minimize error but you
tend to maximize
evaluation right uh it's also not
unsupervised learning so unsupervised
learning you have some kind of an input
right that goes to the agent and then it
figures out what are the patterns for
the in the input right here you have
some kind of an evaluation and you are
expected to produce an action in
response to the input it is not simply
pattern deduction right so you might
want to dedu patterns in the input so
that you know what is the right response
to give but that is not the primary goal
right but in uh unsupervised learning
the pattern deduction itself is the
primary goal so that is the difference
right so here is this one slide which I
think is uh kind of uh the soulle of
reinforcement learning right um it's
called temporal difference so I I I'll
explain it little more detail in in a
couple of slides uh but the intuition
here right so if you if you remember the
Pavlov's dog experiment right what was
the dog doing it was predicting the
outcome of the Bell you know if the Bell
Rings there is an outcome that's going
to happen it's predicting the outcome
which is food is going to happen and
then it was reacting appropriate to the
outcome right so most of reinforcement
learning you're going to be predicting
some kind of outcome that's going to
happen see am I going to get a reward if
I do this or if or am I going to not get
a reward right am I going to win this
game if I make this move or am I not
going to win this game right so I'm
trying to always trying to predict the
outcome right the outcome here is the
amount of reward or punishment I'm going
to get right this is essentially what
I'm trying to predict at every point
right so the intuition behind uh the
what is called temporal difference
learning is the following right so the
prediction that I make at time t + 1
okay of what will be the eventual
outcome let us say I'm playing a game
right I'm going to say I'm going to win
now I'm very sure I'm going to win now
right so I can say that with a greater
confidence when I'm closer to the end of
the
game then I can at the beginning of the
game right so I have all the pieces set
up right if I'm going to sit there then
and say I'm going to win the game right
it's most probably wishful
thinking right but then you have played
the game for like 30 minutes or
something and there are like five pieces
left on the board now I'm going to say
I'm going to win the game now I say I'm
going to win the game that's a much more
confident prediction than what I did at
the beginning right so taking this to
the extreme right so the prediction I
make at t +
1 is probably more accurate than the
prediction I make at T
corre the prediction I make at t + 1 is
more accurate than the prediction I make
at T So if I want to improve the
prediction I make a t what can I do I
can look go forward in time right
basically go to the next let the clock
tick over and see what is the prediction
I'll make at time t+ one with additional
knowledge I'm getting right I would have
moved one step closer to the end of the
game so I know I know it's little bit
better about the game right I don't know
how the game is proceeding and I can now
make a prediction about whether I'll win
or lose right and use this go back and
modify the prediction I make it time
T right at T I think there is a pro
possibility of say probability of 6 of
me winning the game okay and then I make
a move then I find out that I'm going to
lose the game with a very high
probability then what will I do is I'll
go back and reduce the probability of
winning that I made at time T so instead
of 6 I'll say okay maybe .55 or
something right so next time I come to
the same state as I was at time T I
won't make the prediction of 6 I'll say
0.55 that's essentially the idea behind
temporal difference learning right so it
has a whole lot of advantages we'll talk
about it a couple of slides down uh but
one one thing is has had a significant
impact in behavioral psychology and in
Neuroscience right so it's widely
accepted that uh animals actually use
some form of temporal difference
learning and in fact there are specific
models right that uh that have been
proposed for temporal difference
learning which seem to explain some of
the uh neurotransmitter behaviors in the
brain yeah supp we are playing a game
and we have 10 moves that we can make
and out of 10 we will select the best
one okay this is the usual scenario so
here the temporal difference is like we
are Sting the move from next to next
move no no no no see at this point I'll
be making a prediction about what is the
probability of winning right it could be
for each of the moves right if I make
this move what is a probability of
ending if I make this move what is the
probability of ending let us say I I
make move two okay and then I go I see a
new position right my opponent responds
to it and then I decide oh my God this
is a much worse move than I thought
earlier so what I'll do is I'll change
the prediction I make for move two in
the previous
state see that the other other moves
will not be affected because the only
move I took was two only about that move
I have additional information therefore
I can go back and change the prediction
I make for move to
alone okay so you you still have the 10
moves you're not changing any of that
yeah we going back and like changing the
entire thing again or just changing the
prediction changing the prediction it's
not like I mean in Ideal World you
should be able to take back a bad move
right except if if it's a parent playing
with the kid I don't think uh those
things are allowed right uh in fact when
I play with my son we have sometimes had
to RND back all the way to the beginning
it'll probably be me asking to do the
reing not him because he'll be drubbing
me in some one of those games but uh
yeah otherwise you can't you just make
the change the prediction so next time
you play the game you'll be better at
it not for that game well basically
you're you're messed up or you did well
I mean so whatever it is yeah uh looking
at RL right so let's look like Tic Tac
to um how many of you have played tic
Taco good oh even you put your hand up
okay
good okay good uh so so in tic Taco so
you have these board positions right and
uh so you make different moves so in the
first this is what I have drawn here is
called a game tree right so I start off
with the initial board which is empty
right and there are um how many possible
branches
there for people making moves nine
possible branches right for excess move
there are nine possible moves I have
nine possible branches and then for each
of these uh I'll have like eight
possible I'm not sure which is the right
TV huh for each of these I have eight
possible branches and they keep going
right so what we are going to be doing
is uh
essentially uh trying to to Let's
formulate this as a reinforcement
learning problem so how will you do this
as a reinforcement learning
problem right so I have all these board
positions right let us say x is the
reinforcement learning agent and O is
the opponent right so initially given a
blank board I allow to choose one among
nine actions right so the the state that
I'm going to see is this BL the the the
excess and was on the board right and
the moves I'll be making are the actions
right so so in the initial position I
have nine actions I make that do I get
any
reward not really there's no natural
reward signal that you can give
essentially the reward that I'm going to
get in this case is if at the end of the
moves if I win I'll get a one if I don't
win I get a
zero right if I win I get a one if I
don't win I get a zero right so what is
going to happen is I'm going to keep
playing this games multiple times right
and at each point right
um yeah okay so there is a note here so
what ises that note
say you have to assume it's an imperfect
opponent right otherwise there's no
point in trying to learn Tic Tac Toe why
Always draw you'll always draw and the
way we have set up the game you're
indifferent between drawing and losing
so you learn nothing I mean basically so
you not even learn to draw okay you'll
just learn
to nothing basically you learn nothing
because you can never win right so
you're never going to get a reward of
one so you'll just be playing randomly
so it's it's a bad bad idea so let's
assume that you have an agent that can
that is imperfect right that makes
mistakes so that you can actually learn
to figure out where the agent makes
mistakes where the opponent makes
mistakes and learn to exploit those
things okay right so your states are
going to be these board positions as you
can see give you a game that is being
played out on the top of the slide right
and the actions you take are in response
to those board positions and finally at
the end of the game right if you win you
get a one if you don't win you get a
zero right sir is it clear sir in cases
like this I mean does it have to be a
binary sort of a reward system I mean
could you have a scale rather there are
three parameters if you lose it zero if
you draw it's point if you win it's one
sure you could even do other things like
if you win it is one if you lose it
minus one so so then would you have a
perfect component and
learn uh yeah you possibly could but you
probably have to play lot lot and lot of
games because the perfect
opponent it's almost impossible for you
to start getting any feedback in the
beginning right you'll always be losing
so it's going to be hard for you to
learn but you'll eventually learn
something yeah it'll take a lot of moves
you'll eventually learn something if I
say that at every Point yeah so when we
learning like at a particular stage the
probability of winning and like when you
update previous state so uh you're
storing information for you're storing
information for each and every state
that you have entered right so how will
it be different from exploring the prop
like State space every time because
after you've done let's say a thousand,
games or a million games you you have
explored a lot of states and you'll have
to store for each state the probability
of you winning at that point and all
that so how will that be different from
exploring it again like why would I know
the probability of winning from there
why would I have to explore it again uh
no I'm uh let's I'm not even told you
how we are going to solve it okay let me
explain that and then you can come back
and ask me these questions okay if you
still have them uh okay great so what
the way we are going to try and solve
this game is as follows right for every
board position I'm going to try and
estimate the reward I'll get if I start
from there and play the game to the
end right every board position I'm going
to look at the reward I'll get if I
start from there and play till the end
now if you think about it what will this
reward con connotate
right so if I win from there I'll get a
one if I lose from there or if I don't
win from there I'll get a
zero right when I say what is the reward
I expect to get starting from this boat
position right it's essentially this
average over multiple games it's some
games I'll win some games I will lose or
I'll not win like some games I win some
games I'll not win so what will this
expected reward
represent after after having played many
many many games like probility the
probability of winning right the reward
is going to represent the probability of
winning in this particular case right if
the reward had not been one right if it
had been something else if it had been
plus five right it would have
been some function of the probability of
winning right or if it had been plus one
for winning minus one for losing and
zero for draw it's something more
complex it's no longer the probability
of winning right it's it's the gain I
expect to get right how what fraction of
games I expect to win over the fraction
of games I expect to lose or something
like that right it becomes a little bit
more complex so the there could be some
interpretation for the value function
but in general it is just the
expected expected reward that I'm going
to get starting from a particular board
position okay so that is what I'm trying
to estimate right let us assume that I
have such
a expectation well defined for me
right say I have such an expectation
well defined right now I come to a
specific position let us say I come I
come to this position here right let's
say I come to this position how will I
decide what is the next move I have to
make sorry whichever next state has
whichever next state has the highest
probability of winning so I just look
ahead to see okay where if I put if I
put the X
here right if I put the X here what is
the probability of wiing if I put the X
here what is the probability of ending
if I put the X here what is the
probability of wining right I do this
for each one of these right and then I
figure out whichever has the highest
probability of ending and I'll put the X
there right so that's how I'm going to
use this
function does it make
sense
yes it's very important so this is this
is something which you should understand
this the Crux of all reinforcement
learning algorithms right I'm going to
learn this function that tells me if
you're are in this state right if you
play things out to the end what will be
the expected payoff that you will get
right whether the Rewards or punishment
or cost whatever you want to call it
what is the expected value you're going
to get and and I want to behave
according to this uh learned function so
when I come to a state I look ahead
figure out which of the next States has
the highest expectation and then go to
that state okay
great how do I learn this
expectation what's the simplest way to
learn the
expectation come to that St from that
fraction
of essentially you keep track of what
happens essentially keep track of the
trajectory through the game tree right
you play a game you go all the way to
the end right so you keep track of the
TR trory and if you win right you go
back along the trajectory and update
every state that you saw on the
trajectory you update the probability of
winning right you just increase it a
little bit or you come to the end of the
game and you found that you have not won
right you go back along the trajectory
decrease the probability of winning a
little bit right alternatively you can
keep the history of all the games you
have played so far right at every after
every game has been completed you can go
back and compute the average probility
of winning across the entire history of
all the games in which you saw that
particular
position right makes sense that's
easiest way of estimating this
probability right but the problem with
this is a you have to wait till the game
ends right or you have to store the
history of all the games you have played
right I mean all of these could be
potential drawbacks okay you can get
around the History part by coming up
with an incremental rule but the main
difficulty here is you have to wait all
the way to the end of the game right
before you can change anything along the
way so Tic Tac to is easy it's like how
many moves can you make in Tic Tac to at
best four right the fifth one is
determined for you right so it's
basically four choices that you can make
right so and
uh that's easy enough to remember right
you can always wait till the end of the
game and then you can always make the
updates right but what if it's a much
more complex situation right what if
you're playing chess
maybe you can wait till the end so what
if you're
cycling maybe you can wait till the
end
huh
exactly we don't know right it depends
on where you're cycling if you're
cycling learning to cycle in it m it's
fine if you're learning to cycle
somewhere on Sardar Patel Road you don't
want to even think about what end is
there right so so so there are some
tasks for which you really like to learn
along the way right so this is where TD
learning comes into comes to help right
I don't think I have that slide anyway
um and I'm not using the fancy thing
where I can draw on
the uh on the projection so let's see if
I can do it here right
um suppose I have come here right and
from here I have played at this point I
know the probability of winning is say4
right so I came here by making a move
from this position so I said we are here
right and we made a uh we know that the
probability of winning from here is a.3
right but I made the move from here to
come here right but here I had thought
my probability of winning was let us say
6 right I thought my probability of
winning was 6 right but then I looked at
my next States and I found that the best
one was3
somehow right so I went there right but
now since the best I can do from here is
3 me saying 6 here there's something
wrong right so I should probably
decrease the probability of winning from
here right so why could it be why could
it have happened that I thought that was
6 but the best among the next was
three maybe the other BR that you
explored
4 that was fully exploded all all of
that was decreased to4 oh the thing is
so that whenever I came to came through
this part right maybe I won before right
the it so happened that when I went
through like this right initially I
would have gone through like this and
played the game right and the examples I
drew I might have actually won some of
those games right so I would have
changed this to 6 right but it's
possible for me to get here by playing a
different sequence of moves
also right so for example to come
here right I could have put the X first
here and then here or I could have put
the X like I did here I put the X first
here and then here right either way I
would I I could have reached this
position right so there are many
combinations in which I could have
reached the same
positions
right just to be nice to these guys
right to reach here there are different
orders in which I could have put the
zeros and the
X's right here we have showing a
specific order the zero was first put
here then put here right the X was first
put here then put here it could very
well be I put the X first here and the O
first here and then I put the X here and
the O here right there could are
multiple ways in this thing was re reach
right so sometimes when I play those
games right I lost right sometimes when
I play this games I won therefore it
turns out that
for due to some random fluctuations
right so sometimes I win when I go
through this specific point and
therefore I have higher evaluation of
winning right but when I went through
the other paths I had a lower evaluation
of winning right but we know that really
doesn't matter what path you went
through in Tic Tac to right once you
reach that point right what is going to
happen further is determined only by
that
point right so what I can do now is take
this
3 right you should to update that point
six
down down down so I I'm very confident
here I think I'll win with the
probability of 6 right but the best
probability I have from the next stage
is3 therefore here I should not be so
confident
right H good point uh that depends on
how stochastic your game is right so if
your game has a lot of variability then
you don't want to make a complete uh you
know commitment to to3 so you might want
to say okay now let me move it little
bit towards 3 right but if it's more or
less a deterministic game then you can
say okay yeah 3 yes sure let me go to
all the way to 3 it depends on the
nature of the game we'll talk about
these issues later yeah but how far down
is a tricky thing right is calling AE
mising yeah it's misleading it's called
game tree usually but it's a game graph
in this case yeah yeah
yeah so uh is is that clear this is this
is an instance of temporal difference
learning so how will I use the the thing
to update is this is called temporal
difference learning okay so there's one
other uh thing which I should uh mention
here right uh if I always take the
move that which I think is the best move
right
now right let's let's talk about it I I
I start tabas I have never played Tic
Tac to before right so I play the game I
play it once I get I get to the end I
win so now what I do I go back right
whether I'm using temporal difference
learning or waiting till the end
updating whatever it is I change the
value of all the moves I have made in
this particular game right so the next
time I come to a board position what am
I going to do I look at all possible
outcomes everything except the one that
I have played will have a zero right and
the one that I have played will have
something slightly higher than
zero I'm going to take that right in
fact it'll be like how many of you watch
the movie groundhog
day it'll be like Groundhog Day I'll be
playing I'll be playing the same game
again and again because that's what
happened to give me a win in the first
time around right that but that might
not be the best way to play this right
so I need to
explore right so I need to explore
multiple options right so I should
should not be always playing the
best best
move right and I should not always be
playing the best move I need to do some
amount of exploration so that I can
figure out if there are better moves
than what I think is currently the best
move right so in tic Taco there is
inherently some kind of noise if your
opponent is random right but if your
opponent is not random and if opponent
is also playing a fixed Rule and if you
are playing greedy then you'll be just
playing very very small fraction of the
game tree and you wouldn't have explored
the rest of the outcomes right so you
have to do some amount of things at
random so that you learn more about the
game right so here is a question for
you when I'm estimating this
probabilities of winning
right let us say I've reached
here I look down right and the action
that gives me the highest highest
probability of winning say gives me a
probability of say8 right but I want to
explore right so I take an action that
gives me a probability say
point4 okay so I'll go from here to
another action that has a probability
point4 right another board position that
has a probability of point4 of winning
so should I use this point 4 to update
this
probability or
not no why
the
learning that you questioning the whole
TD idea one with that particular
sequence and now you're exploring it so
you shouldn't update it when you're
exploring you should probably wait for
the
end and or not just ignore the
exploration okay any any other answer
you have to update it because you're
learning that move whether it will be a
good move or a bad move will be found
out I have to update the value of that
move I agree do I update the value of
winning from the previous board position
was the question so that point 4 I'll
have to change right but do I change the
point8 that was a question the point8
was a probability of winning from here
right I look or whatever was the prob
let say I had a probability of wining of
6 from here I look at the bottom and the
best probability of wining says 8 but
then I take because I'm exploring I take
an action that has a probability of
winning of point4 right the question is
do I go back and change the
6 towards point 4 or do I leave the 6 as
it is unless this goes over sorry
un that won't go right I'm exploring
right I mean this is will be necessarily
be less than point8 this will be 4 that
will be 6 so the question here is see
one way of arguing about this is to say
that hey if I'm playing to win right
I'll play the best action from here
right and the best action say is8
therefore I should not penalize it for
the bad action which is point4 which I
did to learn more about the system
that's one way of thinking about it
another way of arguing is to say that
hey no no this is how I am actually
behaving now right so I should give you
the probability of winning
about about the current behavior policy
right it should not be some other ideal
policy it should be about what I'm
behaving currently and therefore I
should update
it right so which one is correct
first or the
second first
one you don't know what the second is
you would say the second one great so
all of you can go write that in your
homework answers okay I think this is
one of the homework questions as well
right are you looking at the question I
know you're browsing you're not paying
attention to me but can you look at the
questions as
well you don't have Network
here icsr network doesn't work
okay there should be a Wi-Fi access
point called icsr Studio or something
no
okay fine do you have the question you
have the book
offline
okay fine yeah but I do believe this is
one of the questions right so otherwise
uh make up a question and write answer
to that so we we we'll make sure that
this is one of the questions yeah but
this is something this this is like I
said I'm going to ask you to think about
the whole Tic Tac to
and many of these answers have relevance
later on in fact there are two different
algorithms one does option one one does
option
two right so so there there's no right
answer or wrong answer right it answer
is it depends
depends yeah so yeah so that's these are
different things that you can think
about in this but I now I told you about
two different ways of learning with tic
tacor one wait till the end and figure
out what the probabilities will be the
other one is keep adapting this as you
go along right and both cases you'll
have to explore that's the tricky part
here in both cases you have to explore
otherwise you'll not learn about the
entire game so this is where the explore
exploit thingy comes in okay yeah sir
how do you know what point to stop
exploring and choosing the best great
great
question different algorithms deal with
it different way that's one of the
crucial uh questions that you have to
answer in uh uh
n
RL so it's called the explore exploit
dma right um so you have to explore to
find out which is the best
action right and you have to exploit
whatever knowledge you have gathered
right uh and uh you have to act
according to the best observations
already made right so this is called
exploitation right so the key one of the
key questions is when do you know you
have explored enough right should I
explore now or should I exploit now
right this is called the explore exploit
dilemma right and uh slightly simpler
version of uh reinforcement learning uh
called Bandit problems okay some
colorfully called Bandit problems yeah
of course he's an expert on Bandit
problems yeah you
can uh the Bandit problems encapsulate
this explore exploit dilemma my God lot
of people are turning and looking at you
know and uh so this is the next chapter
we're going to look at so probably in
the next class I'll start uh plunging
into Bandit problems in more detail uh
but so this will ignore a whole bunch of
other things like the delayed rewards
you know the sequential decisions and
other things even in the absence of all
of these other complications right even
if I say that your all your problem is
you have to take an action and you'll
get a reward okay your goal is to pick
the action that gives the highest reward
I give you 10 actions you have to pick
the action that gives you the highest
reward right but the problem is you
don't know what is
the the probability distribution from
which these rewards are
coming right so you'll have to do some
exploration I I have to actually do
every action at least
once okay to know what will be the
reward even if they are deterministic
right so I can't I can't say which is
the best action before I try every
action at least once if it deterministic
it's fine I can just try every action
once and I know what is the
payoff right but if it stochastic I have
to try every action multiple times right
how many times do you have to try it
depends on the variability of the
distribution right so these are subtle
questions which we'll talk about as we
look at the next chapter in
the uh the first chapter in the book
uh the first uh real chapter in the book
okay there's intro chapter which talks
about tic taco and a whole bunch of
other things and uh
yeah we just stop soon not sure want to
do all of
this yeah so we'll come back and talk
about all of these uh later right so I I
thought I would uh uh not spend enough
time talking about the general
background of RL and applications so I
put in a little bit more slides I
typically do this on the board right so
I'll do this on the board when I get to
chapter 3 right and so one one thing
which I wanted to tell you was uh this
right uh there are are uh you know two
classes of algorithms that we will be
talking about so one of them is based on
what's called dynamic programming right
uh so dynamic programming um how many of
you know what dynamic programming
is I expect at least 23 hands up and I
have the mechanical engineers putting
their hands up not the Cs
guys really you don't know what dynamic
programming is huh
something wrong with your hand
then okay fine so what what essential
idea behind Dynamic I I'll talk again
I'll talk as as usual with other things
we'll dwell in this in larger detail the
essential idea behind dynamic
programming is you'll be using some kind
of repeated structure in the problem
right so and to solve the problem more
efficiently right suppose I have I have
a solution that I can give for a problem
of say size n right then I'll try to see
if I can use that for defining the
solution for the problem of size n plus
one right so some kind of a repeated
substructure in the problems right uh a
very very rough way of describing what
dynamic programming is right uh so for
example one way of thinking about
dynamic programming is I have this game
tree right so I look at the values of
winning or or the expectations of
winning from all of these steps right
I'll use these
in order to compute the value of winning
or the the probability of winning from
this
state right so if you think about it if
if from here if I'm going to take say n
steps from here how many steps would you
expect me to take n minus one steps
right so I look at the probability of
winning when I when I have only n minus
one steps left right I'll estimate that
first I'll use that solution for
estimating the probability of winning
when I have n steps
left right so that's a the idea behind
dynamic programming and so what we will
do is uh well we will talk about how do
you use Dynamic programing to solve
reinforcement learning problems right
and then we'll talk about various
reinforcement learning methods which are
essentially online approximate dynamic
programming you know so they are uh they
use dynamic programming ideas but they
don't have any knowledge of the System
Dynamics right so the P the P and R will
other things will come clear later and
uh so all you do now is instead of
having the entire
outcome and using that for estimating
the probability of winning here right
I'm going to just use one step that I
take through the tree right I use just
what happens in this one step I'll use
that in order to update the probability
of wining here right so instead of using
the entire outcome right as in dynamic
programming in reinforcement learning
methods we'll be using samples that you
are getting through the state space okay
this is the TD method in the other
method I explained to in uh for Tic Tac
to what would you do your sample will
run all the way to the end right and
you'll use that to update so that's the
two different ways of using samples yeah
so uh so in this uh in this case we have
the updating of s of T will be
determined by the value in s t + 1 right
so the value of s+1 should be computed
first yeah and so since s+1 depends on S
plus2 again that should be computed
first so won't this be the same thing as
exploring the whole all the way down and
then Computing say let us if you're
doing it for the first time right the
first time down the tree there will be
no updates
actually because st+ one will also be
zero St will also be zero the first time
you go down there will be no updates but
once you reach an end then from there
you'll start updating the previous day
so the next time you go down the tree
then it'll keep going further up
uh uh I I don't understand how this is
different from updating at the end of
whether you won the game or whether you
lost the game
um whether he won the game or lost the
game I actually I'm taking the exact
outcome that happened in that particular
trial right that particular game and I
used that to change my
probabilities right but here I'm not
just taking the outcome of that
particular game right I'm looking at the
expected value of winning from the next
board position
right so if I wait till all the way here
and I say I won and I take this and
update St then I'll be only updating it
with the fact whether I won or not okay
but if I'm updating it from St +1 see I
could have reached St plus1 multiple
ways before right when I'm doing the
updation from St plus1 it's essentially
the average accumulated over all the
previous trails that I'll be using right
so if I play all the way to the end and
update it it'll be with a one or a zero
but st+ one could be anywhere between 1
and zero depending on what's the
probability ofing so I'll be using that
value for updation so that's the crucial
difference okay so there are many
different solution methods so there are
all this which are called temporal
difference methods so these are all
different algorithms TD Lambda Q
learning sarca actor critic so on so
forth right and then there is a all
search of algorithms which called policy
search algorithms and then there is uh
dynamic programming so we will actually
look at uh each of these classes of
algorithms in the uh the next few
lectures right these are all essentially
uh mostly from the textbook except
policy search algorithms uh which I will
be covering from other material right
and there are a whole bunch of other
applications for
RL right so you could
uh they're all over the place as you
could see optimal control optimal
optimization or psychology neuros
science so that's one of the reasons I
was asking is there anyone from biotech
because uh biotech people do use
reinforcement learning a lot and usually
there are one or two people in in in the
RL class so be surprised or maybe that
is that was a BoTech register according
to the academic
website maybe they just gave up in cs36
and went
back I don't know right so here is the
the most recent uh hot thing that came
from RL right uh more game playing and
for a change it's not from IBM right
it's from Google uh but the company that
actually uh built the first uh this
arcade game playing engine was called
Deep Mind and as soon as deep mind built
a successful engine Google bought them
right and so now it's Google deep mind
uh but it's a separate entity right it's
it's not part of Google it's Google Deep
Mind operates out of London and they're
doing all kinds of interesting stuff uh
many of the hot uh advances very recent
advances in the last year or so in
reinforcement learning seem to be coming
out of Deep Mind uh so what they did was
how many of you know about this Atari
games right everyone knows about Atari
games people are getting
tired really no one has played
Pac-Man ah yeah how about how about
pong breakout Space Invaders come on on
yeah anyway so what happened was this
this team in University of Alberta okay
which put out this what they call the AL
the arcade learning Atari learning
environment or arcade learning
environment uh which essentially uh they
allowed computers to play these games
right these Atari games and what the
Deep Mind fellows came up with is a
reinforcement learning agent that
learned to play these games from
scratch right just by looking at the
screen okay that's all the input it was
getting just the pixels from the screen
the raw pixels from the screen were
given as inputs to it it used a very
complex neural network so it's it's a
deep deep learning uh deep Network right
and it is considered one of the hardest
learning problems solved by a computer
and I think I believe it's a one the
only computational reinforcement
learning paper ever to appear in nature
right so usually it's very hard for uh
non natural science people to population
nature right kind of obvious right it's
usually hard for computer science folks
to population nature but uh uh this was
uh uh toted touted as a next step in
trying to understand how humans process
inputs blah blah blah all kinds of
marketing jargon right uh but more
importantly than anything else about
this it's
reproducible so I told you about uh I
think that's a warning sign for me to
stop so I told you about the helicopter
right so that's basically Stanford and
Bur or the two people who get the
helicopter to fly I told you about the
the back gam player it's like Jerry Taro
is a one person who gets the back gamon
player to work right uh partly because
all the input features he uses in there
are proprietary but partly because it's
a very hard problem to solve right what
is amazing thing about this Atari game
engine is that uh these guys have
released a
cord right you can if you have enough
powerful gpus right you can set it up
here and get it to play and get a
reasonably uh working uh engine right
that plays plays the Atari games that's
the amazing thing about it that it's
reproducible as opposed to many of the
other things uh other success stories
other success stories we've had in the
past so I do believe I have just one
more slide after this so let's see if
this will
work okay
so if you have any doubts the green one
is the learning agent
no no this just sped up for you to see I
mean it's not like the game is
progressing at the same right but you
can see the the scores
though mind it was not given a
reward okay is just given the screen
okay never never got a reward for
winning or anything you have to
understand that the pixels on the top
are
rewarding and if you give it rewards it
becomes cheating
right what is
it
yeah which is what they did they did
they did add a game over which is which
the the AL purists consider as cheating
but uh yeah they did add a game over
sign yeah so the longer you keep it
going the better it is
basically
right I think this is getting boring
right so it's it's learned
yeah so this is a
sequest so you have to swim and
then sink down get some things and come
up so sequest is a game that it never
learned to do greatly on though
sequence is not something which it
learned to solve well so there are a few
games like this so when they initially
publish the paper I think they had like
like 45 or 46 out of the 50 a league
games uh they were able to play well and
I think in 43 of them it had better than
human
performance and I think the current
state is they have like one game that
doesn't play well right and they have
better than human performance in like 48
of those games or something so which is
this is amazing if you think about
it right so these are all lot of
references uh but but we'll be using the
SAT and B textbook uh the second edition
We There is a pre-release copy which
rich saton is continuously updating on
his web page right and uh a very very
short introduction to uh uh reinfor
learning in Tom Mitchell's book and
that's a chapter in Russell and norw and
uh if you're interested in looking at
the the
Neuroscience uh perspective of
reinforcement learning or the history of
how Behavioral psychology models evolve
to temporal difference learning uh you
can look at Dian and Abott uh that's one
chapter on reinforcement learning uh you
don't have to understand the
Neuroscience to understand the RL
chapter so don't get put off by the
title of the book right and then the
more
mathematically uh well grounded
introduction to reinforcement learning
would be from bers and cist so apart
from this we'll use one book which is uh
Mark of Deion processes by puterman
right we'll use certain chapters from PU
and that's just for us to understand
mdps better mation process better
[Applause]